[MUSIC]
預先註冊
In the previous lectures,
前面的課程中
we've talked about the importance of controlling your type I error rate.
談到控制型一錯誤率的重要性
An increasingly popular way to make sure that people adequately control their type
目前能適當控制型一錯誤率的方式是預先註冊
I error rates is pre-registration,
where you specify what you're going to do before you perform the study.
這是由研究者自已開始研究前先備份研究計畫
And then after, when you've collected the data, you can just follow this
遵守計畫要點，處理收集的資料
pre-registered plan to make sure that your type I error rate is nicely controlled.
讓型一錯誤率得到最佳控制
Let's talk a little bit about why this is important, and how you can pre-register
本講介紹預先註冊的重要性
and what you need to take care of when you make a pre-registration.
以及規劃預先註冊的建議
Let's first focus on the importance of pre-registration.
首先談預先註冊的重要性
Why do we need to do this?
為何我們需要這麼做？
Now, this is an example where you don't really need to read the fine print here,
投影片裡的例子你不需要仔細閱讀
I'll explain it to you.
讓我解釋給你聽
This is the first study in an article by Daryl Bem about precognition.
這段文字來自Daryl Bem發表的超感知覺論文
And in his experiment,
這篇論文的第一個研究
he had 100 participants who performed a sort of reversed priming task.
招募100位參與者進行反向促發實驗
Normally, people have to categorize stimuli by pressing one of two buttons,
一般的實驗是讓人在看過刺激之後
and this happens, of course, after they have seen the stimulus.
使用兩個反應按鍵分類刺激
But here this was reversed.
只是這個實驗反過來做
So people first made a choice, they pressed one or the other button.
他請人先按鍵再看刺激
And only then did they see the stimulus that they were supposed to respond to.
刺激出現後才知道有沒有按對
So if they could predict the future,
如果人可以預測未來
you would expect that they were right, more than guessing average.
反應正確率應該比純粹猜測還高
And in this case, we see that's there was a situation where a number of different
這一系列研究操弄了很多種類的刺激
types of stimuli were used.
The reported result here, the main result, is their performance on erotic stimuli.
投影片這段報告是情色類刺激的實驗結果
But there are a lot of other,
論文中還有其他種類刺激的實驗報告
不過都沒有發現顯著差異
different types of stimuli that were used where no differences were found.
論文中還有其他種類刺激的實驗報告
不過都沒有發現顯著差異
So for example, although the performance was higher than chance on the erotic
情色類的反應表現有顯著高於純粹猜測
stimuli, there were no differences on negative stimuli or romantic stimuli.
而負面訊息與浪漫類刺激都沒有發現差異
Now if you see this, this sort of makes you wonder,
講到這裡，你也許會好奇
is this really the main prediction that this researcher set out to test?
這樣的結果真的符合作者的預測嗎？
If you look at the p-value, if you do the math and you have a Bonferroni correction,
看到報告裡的p值，回想前面提到的Bonferroni校正
you want to control the type I error rate for all the possible combinations,
你會想到要控制所有種類的型一錯誤率
then this would actually not be statistically significant if
如果全部種類的結果都考慮進來
we would have controlled our error rate for all possible comparisons.
這段文字裡沒有一個p值低於統計顯著水準
So you see that it's very important to specify which test you are really
由此可知在進行分析前，
預先說明要做的檢定是很重要的
interested in before you do the analysis,
to make sure that other people who read
可以讓讀者知道你的處理符合統計原則
your article are also convinced that your results and your findings are credible.
讓報告的結果與發現更加可信
Now, here we see that there's a wide range of options of how to analyze your data,
這張漫畫示意分析資料的操作有兩個極端
ranging from very exploratory analysis, you just look at your data and
一邊是探索性分析，只是概覽資料
anything that happens to stand out you consider as an informative result,
任何分析產物都被當成有意義的結果
to a situation where you slightly torture your data.
這個情況會有拷問資料的情況
You don't really look at everything that's possible, but you have one hypothesis,
如果你有一個假設，就不會看所有分析產物是有意義的
but you look at it from this side or
這就要把目光移向另一端
from that side, to a situation where research is purely confirmatory.
了解驗證性分析的重點是
You specify what you want to do, you perform the experiment and
預先表列待辦事項、照表執行實驗
you analyze the data.
以及分析資料
So this is from a research article by Wagenmakers and colleagues where they
以上所談就是來自這張插圖的原始出處
argue for the necessity of having a purely confirmatory research agenda.
Wagenmakers與同儕發表說明驗證性研究綱領的論文
We can see examples in the scientific literature for
還有個例子來自一篇之後的課程會談
where this would make sense, for example, in a paper about p-curve analysis,
有關p-curve分析的論文
a topic we'll come back to later.
說明註冊研究的重要性
Simonsohn and colleagues analyzed
a set of studies from the Journal
作者Simonsohn等人分析一系列
發表於人格與社會心理學論文的數據
of Personality and Social Psychology,
作者Simonsohn等人分析一系列
發表於人格與社會心理學論文的數據
where the researchers reported
the results only with a covariate.
這些數據都有報告共變量分析
So you can do a covariate analysis, and
一般來說做共變量分析
it might really answer the question that you are asking.
是為了澄清無法直接從結果回答的一些問題
But what we also know is that people are sometimes using a covariate
但是圈內人都知道有時共變量分析
as a flexible way to look at their data from a different perspective
會被用做降低主要效果p值的手段
with the goal to reduce the level of the p-value.
So their initial analysis might not show a statistically significant effect, but
這些人做分析後發現主要效果並未統計顯著
then they play around with their data just a little bit until
就拿其他變項進來做共變量分析
adding a covariate would make a statistical analysis significant.
做到其中一個讓主要效果的統計值顯著
So when they look at a set of studies that use covariates, they see that the p-curve
所以Simonsohn挑出有做共變量分析的論文
analysis shows that these studies actually lack evidential value.
p-curve分析發現這些研究結果缺乏證據價值
So using this flexibility leads to a a set of studies in the scientific literature
由此可見研究者的操作彈性已讓部分科學文獻
that really don't tell us anything about what's likely to be true.
充斥不具實質證據的研究結果
So recently, people in psychology have been starting to think about how can we
現在心理學研究者開始思考
如何改善研究操作彈性帶來的問題
change this type of flexibility?
現在心理學研究者開始思考
如何改善研究操作彈性帶來的問題
How can we make sure that people actually report the analysis that they
如何確認研究者報告的分析是從一開始就設計好的？
set out to do in the beginning?
And an increasingly popular solution is the use of registered reports,
註冊報告是正在興起的模式
where people write down their predictions before they perform the data collection.
報告作者要在開始收集資料前寫出報告
And then they analyze their data just by following these reports.
接著要按照報告分析資料
Now, it's very important that this specifies the plan of the analysis of
報告的重點是陳列驗證主要假設的
所有分析計畫細節
the main hypothesis.
報告的重點是陳列驗證主要假設的
所有分析計畫細節
Of course, it doesn't prevent you from exploring your data.
當然，報告作者還是可做探索性分析
This is perfectly fine, but it just differentiates between pre-registered,
這種模式是介於預先註冊的驗證性研究
與探索性研究之間
confirmatory research and more exploratory research.
這種模式是介於預先註冊的驗證性研究
與探索性研究之間
So in this way pre-registration formalizes the Type 1 error control.
預先註冊有型一錯誤的控制標準措施
You have a very specific plan that you set out to do, and all the tests that you do
一開始要設定詳盡的分析計畫
that follow your pre-registered hypothesis have a controlled Type 1 error rate.
並按照預先設定的控制條件進行所有檢定
For other analysis, more exploratory analysis,
至於偏向探索性的分析
you can test anything that you'd like.
研究者可以按需要執行
But in this case, your error rate is inflated to an unknown level, so
但是要自負型一錯誤率膨脹的風險
you don't really know the probability that you're making a false positive result.
沒有人告訴你結果是偽陽性的機率有多高
Does this matter?
這麼做值得嗎？
Aren't we making life a lot more complicated by asking researchers to
有沒有研究者覺得預先註冊會增加工作負擔？
pre- register their hypothesis?
Well, there's some data to show that there is indeed a benefit of pre-registering and
現在已有資料證實預先註冊的好處
preventing this flexibility.
可以降低操作彈性的問題
This is from an analysis of a set of studies that were large,
這張圖來自醫藥領域的大數據分析
randomized, controlled trials in medicine, either before it was
這個領域有執行隨機化臨床試驗前要在網站預先註冊的政策
formally required to pre-register your study, the design and
圖中左右兩側的點顯示政策上路前與上路後的研究品質
the analysis plan in clinical trials.gov, and after this was formally required.
So on the left, we see that from all the big, randomized control trials,
圖左側是上路前的臨床試驗結果
some don't show any statistically significant result, but many actually do.
雖然其中有不少並沒有達到統計顯著
17 out of 30 studies before 2000 actually show a significant result.
但是30項裡總共有17項報告統計顯著結果
After pre-registration became required, this percentage drops to only 2 out of 25.
政策上路後25項研究只有2項有統計顯著結果
Now, this is an indication that if we
ask people to specify their hypothesis
這項資料告訴我們只要研究者預先註冊
beforehand, they don't always succeed in confirming their hypothesis,
並不會總是成功地驗證假設
which is totally fine, of course.
總體而言這是好的發展
It's very important to realize that
your prediction did not hold up.
了解不是每個預測都能被支持是很重要的
There might have been new insights and exploratory analyses in the studies done
這項資料能讓我們透視西元2000年後的發展
after 2000, but these need to confirmed in follow-up research.
不過更多利弊還需要更進一步的確認
So we see that the main goal of pre-registration is distinguishing
談到現在你已知道預先註冊的重點是
confirmatory research from exploratory research.
區分驗證性研究與探索性研究
This is sometimes called HARKing, hypothesizing after the results are known.
後者有時稱為"事後諸葛"(HARKing)
If we think back to the study we described in the beginning about precognition,
拿一開始提的超感知覺研究來說
where a researcher tests all sorts of hypotheses, then after looking at
研究者測試所有可行的假設
the data, a researcher might think, of course, there' s something very special
看過資料後也許想到能解釋情色類刺激有差異
about erotic stimuli that's not present in negative stimuli or in romantic stimuli.
但負向訊息或浪漫類無差異的絕佳說法
And this researcher might come up with a hypothesis of why it's actually very
論文作者能把這樣的說法寫成能在實驗前做出預測
plausible that an effect has occurred.
But this is hypothesizing　after the results are known.
實際是分析結果之後才提出假設
This is creating a hypothesis　based on the observed data, and
這種假設是有了資料才被創造出來
that's reversing the empirical cycle.
與科學研究的流程完全相反
When you're exploring data,　you can perform a hypothesis test, but
探索性研究可以展現可行的假設
you can't test a hypothesis.
但不能測試假設
This is a statement by De Groot,　who already pointed this out in the 1950s.
這是荷蘭心理學家De Groot在1950年代提出的主張
The point here is that it's perfectly fine to explore data and
探索資料中任何可能引出有趣想法的訊息是好的
look around, patterns that you might find.
But when you do this, you cannot test whether this hypothesis is actually true
但是若你在事前還沒想到這樣的假設
because what you have done, you have actually
不能用啟發想法的資料
tested a hypothesis on the same data set that was used to generate it.
測試事後才形成的假設
The alpha level in this case is unknown, it has inflated to an unknown extent.
"事後諸葛"導致型一錯誤膨脹的程度還未可估算
So you can never be sure whether this is a type I error or not.
沒人知道這類文獻的型一錯誤率有多少
And you can make no statement about the frequency of Type I errors in the long
也無法得知這類研究操作的長遠影響
run, if you are allowing yourself to be so flexible.
累積的文獻品質是好是壞
So when you pre-register your study, what are things that you need to specify?
要提出一項預先註冊研究，有什麼要注意的呢？
Well, as we've seen,
前一講已學到
optional stopping is one way in which you can inflate your Type I error rate.
中停分析是最可能膨脹型一錯誤率的因素
So one thing that you have to do is justify your sample size.
針對這點能做的是明確宣告要收集的樣本數
Of course, thinking about your sample size before you collect
當然事前宣告樣本數也能有效控制型二錯誤率
data is also very useful in controlling your type II error rate.
Thinking about how many people you need will control both these error rates, but
想清楚要招募多少人能控制兩種錯誤
it will fix the type I error rate to whatever level you've specified.
更能將型一錯誤率固定在設定好的水準
This is sometimes known as the stopping rule.
有時也會遇上必須的中停情況
It can be anything, you can collect data until it starts to rain outside or
像是要在下雨天才能收集資料
until the week is over, anything that you want.
要隔一個星期才能找回受試者等等
In a later lecture, we'll talk about justifying your sample sizes.
之後有一講會談界定樣本數的做法
Another thing you need to specify is the independent variable and
第二點是事先明列統計檢定中的獨變項與依變項
the dependent variable for each test that you want to do.
What is it that you're actually going to analyze?
那些變項是要放進分析程序的？
What are the conditions in your study?
那些變項是標記實驗條件？
And what are the dependent variables with which you measure whatever type of
那些依變項的數值是根據預測所做的測量？
effect you predict?
For the dependent variable, it might be relevant to say,
依變項的說明清單可以報告
I'm using a questionnaire and these are the items that I will average.
使用的問題選項以及要計算平均的題目
And I will perform my analysis on this average score.
如何處理平均得分的方式等等
It matters whether you do this, or maybe use one of all these items.
這些說明有關要不要做、該不該全做等彈性
So this flexibility should be prevented by specifying what the DV is.
明確說明依變項的處置能避免這類彈性操作
Finally, you should describe your analysis plan.
最後，清楚描述分析計畫
How are you going to analyze your data, and
你要如何分析資料
which statistical tests do you plan to perform?
要使用什麼統計檢定
This includes specifying things like the alpha level that you want to use for
包括顯著水準的設定都要交待
each test.
How are you going to correct for multiple comparisons, or
像是如何校正多重比較
do you want to use a 5% error rate or a 1% error rate or a 10% error rate?
型一錯誤率設定是5%,1%或10%
What do you think is sensible?
解釋為何如此設定是夠靈敏的
It also requires you to specify things like data cleaning.
其他要交待的有如何清理原始資料
What is an outlier, and
如何標記極端值
how you're going to remove outliers when they're problematic.
以及移除極端值是基於什麼品質條件
Now, we see that journals are increasingly starting to use these pre-registered
越來越多期刊開始接受預先註冊
studies.
In this example, journal Perspectives on Psychological Science is using
以「心理科學觀點」為例
pre-registered protocols to perform large-scale replication studies,
這本期刊接受大型再現研究的預先註冊
where a lot of people team up and perform a pre-registered replication of
這是號召多人合作，進行主題文獻的註冊再現研究
an existing study in the scientific literature.
There's a clear benefit of pre-registering your studies, especially when the journal
預先註冊有顯而易見的好處
where you're going to submit your research allows for these pre-registered reports.
特別是有期刊接受你提出預先註冊報告
So you can do this for a replication study, but
不只可以做再現研究
you can also do it for very novel research.
也可以做原創研究
This means that based on the plan that you have, you'll get comments from
這樣的好處是提出計畫之後
experts in the field that tell you how to improve your study design before you have
你能收到同行專家給予改善設計的建議
put in all the effort to collect the data, analyze the data, and write the report.
接著再收集資料，分析結果與撰寫報告
Compared to the traditional system, where you only get all this feedback and
有別於傳統投稿模式，同行回饋是
these comments after you already did all the work.
完成全部工作之後才會收到
There's a big benefit because these peer reviews before you collect the data will
如此的好處是你在收集資料之前
allow you to improve your study design.
就能根據同行建議改善設計
So instead of doing all the hard work, and then being told by reviewers that you made
而非好不容易完成研究之後
你才收到負評滿滿的同儕評審
a mistake or you should have taken into account something that you didn't see,
而非好不容易完成研究之後
你才收到負評滿滿的同儕評審
you can get this feedback before you collect the data.
預先註冊讓你收集資料前就知道問題
So this is a very efficient way to make sure that you perform a well-designed
這能有效地研究者獲得同儕審查的認可之後
study, where your peer reviewers agree that this is, indeed,
執行良好設計的研究
the best approach to study a specific topic.
這種模式對特定主題的研究特別有利
And that the results will be informative,
結果不論有沒有統計顯著
也是有益科學發展的資訊
regardless of whether they
are statistically significant or not.
結果不論有沒有統計顯著
也是有益科學發展的資訊
And this is another very important benefit of these registered reports.
這是註冊報告的另一個好處
When you've submitted your study design for publication, the peer reviewers
透過發表研究設計
give you some suggestions to improve the way that you want to study this topic.
同行評審給予改善設計的建議
The editor of the journal will say as long as you follow this pre-registered design,
期刊主編可向投稿註冊報告的作者宣言
regardless of the outcome of the study, we will publish it.
只要如實按表操作，不管結果如何，必定完整發表
Now, we know that publication bias is a huge problem in the scientific literature.
出版偏誤充斥科學文獻是不可忽視的問題
There are way more study results that turn out to be statistically significant,
主觀預期經由很多方式引導發表的研究結果
as you would expect.
The reason for this is that people don't publish their non-significant findings or,
導致出版偏誤的主因是很多人不想發表不顯著的結果
when they are submitted for publication, journals don't accept them.
尤其是很多期刊會拒絕不顯著的結果
Now, this problem is prevented by these registered reports because people say if
註冊報告能避免這樣的問題
you follow this plan, we will publish the results no matter what the outcome.
只要按計畫操作，不管是什麼樣的結果，期刊都會刊出
So this is an important benefit, and if you do a challenging study,
對於挑戰前人的研究，這更是一項優勢
it's very worthwhile to consider following these registered report rules.
值得我們考慮採取註冊研究規範的好處
There's some other benefits to pre-registering your studies.
預先註冊還有一些值得一提的好處
For example, you can do less conventional, but more efficient, designs.
像是有些作法不保守、卻更有效率的研究設計
We already discussed how you can improve
前一講提到採用單側檢定能提高檢定力
the statistical power of your test by performing a one-sided test.
This also controls the error rate.
這辦法也能控制型一錯誤率
But you're saying that you have a directional prediction.
不過這辦法用在有方向性預測才好
And if this is the case,
如果條件許可
then you can be more efficient in designing a well-powered study.
就能在有高考驗力的研究裡發揮作用
However, people always think that there's something wrong with people who report
只是許多人仍存有成見，
覺得這辦法是用來降低p值的技倆
one-sided tests because it's very often used as a way to reduce the p-value.
只是許多人仍存有成見，
覺得這辦法是用來降低p值的技倆
So in this pre-registered report, you can write down that you have a directional
不過你可以在在註冊報告裡寫清楚方向性假設
prediction, you'll do a one-sided test, and
說明單側檢定的必要性
you can reap the benefits of this directional hypothesis.
就可以用清晰的假設對抗成見
Now, there's some places where you can pre-register your study design.
你可運用現成的網路平台佈置預先註冊
You can visit the Open Science Framework, or websites such as AsPredicted.org.
像是Open Science Framework
或AsPredicted.org
You can see what's required for
根據你的實際需要
you to pre-register your study, which information you need to fill out.
選擇合適的平台預先註冊你的研究
Now, if you do this, you can keep this pre-registration private so
這些平台可以設定不公開預先註冊內容
you don't need to publish it online so that everybody can see what you do.
有需要的話，不必一開始就在網路上完全公開
It is possible, but you can just keep it private until the moment
你可以設定不公開期限
that you're going to submit your results for publication.
直到正式向期刊投稿為止
And you can say, look, these are the results that I'm presenting, and
你可以昭告天下，剛完成的研究結果
you can see that this is exactly what I predicted when I designed the study.
是完全符合最初設計時的預測
So in this lecture,
簡單總結
we've seen that pre-registration is a novel, but very useful,
預先註冊是一種新穎的研究模式
solution to distinguish exploratory research from confirmatory research.
但是能區分探索性與驗證性的研究操作
And in doing so,
按規範操作的話
it allows you to adequately control your type I error rates.
能控制型一錯誤率在合理範圍之內
[MUSIC]
影片結束